Guide to the James B. Sumner papers, 1908-1958.
Sumner, James B. papers, 1908-1958.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
James B. Sumner papers, 1908-1958.
29-2-671
James Batcheller Sumner, 1887-1955.
8 cubic ft.
Correspondence, lecture notes, printed material, photographs, notebooks, ephemera.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence concerning the organization of biochemical research in Brazil, notes for addresses and lectures, drafts and reprints of articles, graphs, photographs, and slides, the Scheele medal (1929), the gold medal and certificate for the Nobel Prize in Chemistry, printed Nobel proceedings, photographs of the ceremony, glass slides made in the course of his research, photographs of fellow scientists, and his chemistry notebook from Harvard. Also, biographical sketches, notes, clippings, and related correspondence used by Professor Leonard A. Maynard in preparation of his memoir of Sumner.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Biochemistry and Director of the Laboratory of Enzyme Chemistry at Cornell University.
Sumner won the Nobel Prize in Chemistry in 1946 for the crystallizations of the enzyme urease.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence concerning the organization of biochemical research in Brazil, notes for addresses and lectures, drafts and reprints of articles, graphs, photographs, and slides, the Scheele medal (1929), the gold medal and certificate for the Nobel Prize in Chemistry, printed Nobel proceedings, photographs of the ceremony, glass slides made in the course of his research, photographs of fellow scientists from Cornell and elsewhere, and his chemistry notebook from Harvard. Also, biographical sketches, notes, clippings, and related correspondence used by Professor Leonard A. Maynard in preparation of his memoir of Sumner, published in 1958 by the National Academy of Sciences.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Sumner, James Batcheller, 1887-1955.; Maynard, Leonard Amby, 1887-1972.
Subjects:
Biochemistry.; Enzymes.; Urease.; Nobel prizes.; Biochemists.; College teachers.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence, research notes
Series II. Course and lecture notes
Series III. Books, reprints
Series IV. Photographs and glass slides
Series V. Recognitions
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence, research notes
  - Sumner Biography - NAS from L.A. Maynard, 1946-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Short Autobiography of J.B. Sumner for Rochester U. talk, Jan. 21, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Corres. Director Acton, Rudolph P. [Univ. Program-Brazil], 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Misc. Corres. concerning Brazil, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Corres. Brazilian General Consulate, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, Henry Allen Moe, Secretary General, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Corres. Rockefeller Foundation, Prof. J. Baeta Vianna, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Corres. Secretary General Ansio Teixeira, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Introducing C.B. Van Niel (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Messenger Lectures (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Nobel Prize Regulations (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Appointments by Cornell University (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Determination of Coenzyme I by O2 used up (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Coenzyme I (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Coenzyme I Determination (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Further Purification of Coenzyme I (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Phosphorus % in Coenzyme I (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pentose Determination in Coenzyme I (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Estimation of Coenzyme I (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Football Protein Method of Preparation, A.L. Dounce (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Third Liver Protein (Footballs) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Liver Catalase (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Football Protein (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Glutathione Hopkins J. Biol. Chem., 84, 267, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Methods of Enzymology, Edited by Colowick & Cohen (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Lycopene Prep. from tomato (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Byxin Prep. of crystalline byxin from annatto (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lipoxidase old note (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Chapter on Enzymes for Hawk, 13th Edition (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Lipoxidase, J.D. Loconti (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - A.D.P. Preparation (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Method for Blood Count (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1. Cori ester synthesis (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 2. Formation of starch from cori ester (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 3. Preparation of phosphorylase - pages rewritten for Hawk (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Antigenic Properties of the Hemagglutinin, Concanavalin A (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Progress Report, Dr. Eric Borel, "Succinic Dehydrogenase" (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Van Buren, Progress Reports (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Fluoridation (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Progress Report, Dr. Herr "Lipase," through Apr. 3, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Mechanism of Encyme Action (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Ferriten from Horse Liver Catalase Preparation (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Starch, Amylase Preparation (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Evaporated Milk Co., Milk Proteins, H.S. Sipple (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Mechanism of Insulin Action (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Copper Det. 1. Tompsett Method 2. (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Phosphylase Calculation of units (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Analysis of Phosphocreatine - Calculated 0.200% P. - Found 0.191% P. (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - [Loose corres. Donald D. Van Slyke, Edward L. Gordy, Wilder D. Bancroft], 1926, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - "Co. A" (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Urease Paper (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - The Biological Importance of the Elements (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Nobel Prize Nominations (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Biliverdin (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - How to take Microphotographs, J.B.S. (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Warburg Manometer Calculations, Dt. of Creatmine Oxolocetic Acid Pref. (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Internal Structure of Proteins (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Sumner-Somers Material (in German) (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Micro Determination of Phosphorous, Sumner Method, 2 to 50 gamma of Phosphorous (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Dry Catalase, Dounce (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Use of Tswett Column, J.B. Sumner (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Operation of the Beckman Spectrophotometer (and others) (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Sheffield Farms (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Sumner Articles (Box 1, Folder 61-62)
  - Biochemistry 203, Preparations to be handed in (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - The Isoelectric Point of Catalase - - - (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Method of Preparation of Lecithinose A - - - (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - The Determination of Glucose - - - (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Determination of Phosphorus, Berenblum - chain method better than others? (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Anticatalase, Don Wood - more work should be done on this, May 1932 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Odor Research (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Chemical Linkages (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - The Use of a Tswett Column (with catalase) (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - How to Review a Book (J. Chem. Ed.) (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Research Funds (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - 1. Am. Cancer Soc., Inc. (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - 2. (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - De Zeenuw Research, Anti-urease, May 8, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Yellow Enzymes - extra copy for 3rd edition of Sumner & Somers (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Ting, Amonia Poisoning (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Fat Extraction Apparatus designed by James B. Sumner (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - N.N.S. by Sugar (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - The use of the D - - - method for sugar with the Photoelectric Colormeter [?] (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Det. of Pyrethrius, J.B. Sumner, Dec. 30, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Test for Dihydrocoenzyme I using Diaphorase (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Horse Liver Catalase Preparation (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Catalase Further Refinements, The action of Try - - - (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - R. Young, Apo-Cytochrome c Reductase as a test for FMN, Feb. 12, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Van Buren, FAD Production by Microorganisms (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Preparation of Dry Catalase (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Research Progress by Beaver [Bever], De Zeeuw, Wood, Nygaard & Young, Nov. 3, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Scheme for Protein Synthesis, A.S. Dounce (Incomplete) (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Cytochrome Oxidase (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Glucurondase (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Riboflavin Synthesis (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Preparation of the Old Yellow Enzyme (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - A Second Crystallizable Beef Liver Protein etc. (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Catalase Activation - Institution Divi Thomae (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Lipoxidase (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Saccharase (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Thrombin and Prothrombin (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Peptide Chain and Nucleic Acid Synthesis (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Glucose Oxidation by Rat Liver (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - [Diphosphopyridine Nucleotide - - -] (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - [Glucose Dehydrogenase] (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Phosphodiesterase (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Glucose Det. (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Bibiverdin (Crystalline by peroxidase and H2O2) (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Estimation of Nucleoprotein and their Hydrolytic Products (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Physiological Detoxification (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Quant [?] Method for Peroxide (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Fourth Liver Protein (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Micro. Det. of Pentoses (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - An Improved Method for the Preparation of Crystalline Carboxypeptidase (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Pyrethrus Det. Curve (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - The Purification of Beta Glucosidase and estimation of Glucosidase activity, J.B. Sumner and S.F. Howell, July 12, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - The Development of Present Day Ideas as to the Chemical Virtues of Enzymes (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Jack Bean Phosphorylase - Best Method - Sumner and Sisler, Apr. 23, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Factors Involved in the Enzymatic Reduction of Cytochrome C (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - I Cytochrome Oxidase (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - II Carotenoid Pigment (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Analytical Methods (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Preparation of
    - 1 Muscle Adenylic Acid (Box 1, Folder 118)
    - 2 Adenvine [?] Triphosphate (Box 1, Folder 118)
    - 3 Pectin Quant. Det. (Box 1, Folder 118)
    - 4 Tokadiaslase (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - B-Glucuronidase - A talk given at Savage Hall by J.B.S. before the research group, May 23, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - A Lecture on Agglutination (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - Corrections and Index for Laboratory Manual - Sumner and Somers, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 121)
  - Enzymes - 4th Edition - material to insert, Nov. 1952 (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - For the 4th Edition of Sumner and Somers, "Chemistry and Properties of Enzymes" (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - 4th Edition, Sumner and Somers (Box 1, Folder 124)
  - For the 4th Edition of Sumner and Somers, "Chemistry and Properties of Enzymes" (Box 1, Folder 125)
  - The Enzymes - Supplement, May 1954 (Box 1, Folder 126)
  - Calculations for Phosphate solution use in Recrystallizing Urease, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - Howell - Ghosts, Purification of Stromata - unpublished (Box 1, Folder 128)
  - Aluminum Hydroxides as Adsorbents (Box 1, Folder 129)
  - Mechanism of Enzyme Action (Box 1, Folder 130)
  - Astor Hotel (Times Square), Dec. 10, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Harvard Lecture, 4:30 p.m., Jan. 16, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Analytical Methods - Sugar Det. and Tests (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Biochemistry 203 - Lecture - Quantitative Methods (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lecture, Oct. 1951 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Trip to Trenton, NJ, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Biographies and Bibliographies of Certain Scientists (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Folen's Ph.D. Students in Biochemistry (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Authors and Subjects for a book (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nominees for National Academy of Science, ca. 1952 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Loose material (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
  - Articles - William Burgess (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Eric Borel (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Earl B. Herr, Jr. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - P.S. Krishman (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Walter Mosemann (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - A.P. Nygaard (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - N.K. Sarkar (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Roger G. Young (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - E.A. Zeller (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Army Chemical Center (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Biochemistry Major Arts and Sciences (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "The Enzymes," Reviews of (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Enzyme Chemistry, Annual Progress Report for Laboratory of (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ford Foundation (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Division of Grants, Public Health Service, Bethesda, Md. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - The Lilly Research Laboratories Grant, Eli Lilly & Co. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Research Corporation Annual Dinner, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Rockefeller Fund for Enzyme Chemistry (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - The Schroeder Foundation (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1955
    - A (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - B (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - C (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - D (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - E (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - F (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - G (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - H (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - I (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - J (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - K (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - L (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - M (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - N (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - O (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - P (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - R (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - S (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - T (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - U (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - V (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - W (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - XYZ (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Series II. Course and lecture notes
  - Harvard College course notes, 1908 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Biochemistry lecture and laboratory notes, ca. 1947-1954 (Box 3, Volume 2)
- Series III. Books, reprints
  - Books by James B. Sumner
    - Chemistry and Methods of Enzymes, James B. Sumner and G. Fred Somers, New York: Academic Press Inc., 1947 (Box 4)
    - Chemistry and Methods of Enzymes (3rd edition), 1953 (Box 4)
    - Laboratory Experiments in Biological Chemistry, Sumner-Somers, New York: Academic Press, Inc., 1949 (Box 4)
    - Textbook of Biological Chemistry, Sumner, New York: The MacMillan Company, 1927 (Box 4)
  - Reprints
    - Sumner, H.A. Torrey, C.H. Fiske, E. Zung, R.S. Hubbard, A. Graham, C.V. Noback, 1910-1926 (Box 4)
    - Sumner, R.G. Holloway, D.B. Hand, K. Myrback, J.S. Kirk, L.O. Poland, 1926-1933 (Box 4)
    - Sumner, J.S. Kirk, I. Fankuchen, S.F. Howell, A. Zeissig, 1933-1936 (Box 4)
    - Sumner, S.F. Howell, A.L. Dounce, N. Gralen, I.-B. Eriksson-Quensel, 1936-1938 (Box 4)
    - Sumner, S.F. Howell, A.L. Dounce, E. Tria, O.D. Frampton, 1938-1940 (Box 4)
    - Sumner, A.L. Dounce, M. Laskowski, V.L. Frampton, Erland C. Gjessing, J.W. Howland, 1940-1943 (Box 4)
    - Sumner, E.B. Sisler, G.F. Somers, E.L. Cosby, M. Nymon, P.S. Krishnan, 1942-1947 (Box 4)
    - Sumner, P.S. Krishnan, G.N. Smith, W.L. Nelson, D.J. O'Kane, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
    - Sumner, P.S. Krishnan, T.L. Sourkes, Y.C. Ting, H.O. Kunkel, W.L. Nelson, T.C. Chow, A.T. Bever, J.H. Northrop, N.K. Sarkar, 1948-1951 (Box 4)
    - Sumner, M.S. Dunn, W. Drell, P.A. Shaffer, w. Mosimann, N.K. Sarker, A.P. Nygaard, F.B. Hutt, A.T. Bever, 1950-1952 (Box 4)
    - Le Prix Nobel en 1946 - Sumner's personal copy of 1946 prize winners (Box 4)
  - Other Books
    - Practical Physiological Chemistry, Philip B. Hawk, Philadelphia: P. Blakiston's Son & Co., 1916 (Box 4)
    - A German-English Dictionary for Chemists, Austin M. Patterson, New York: John Wiley & Sons, Inc., 1917 (Box 4)
    - American Men of Science, 4th Edition, New York: The Science Press, 1927 (Box 4)
  - Bound Papers
    - Burlingham, Kenneth, The Effect of Plant Growth Substances on Respiratory Metabolism and the Relation of this to Growth, 1955 (Box 4)
    - Green, D.E., Biochemical Methods (Box 4)
    - List of journals/locations (Box 10)
- Series IV. Photographs and glass slides
  - Cornell Alumni dinner, 1947-02-17 (Mapcase-folder 1, Folder 1)
  - Panoramic photo of Annual Meeting of the Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology, 1923 (Mapcase-folder 2)
  - Class of 1918 (2 copies) (Box 5)
  - Faculty and Students of Cornell Medical College (?), ca. 1928-1932 (Box 5)
  - Cornell University Faculty group photograph, ca. 1928 (Box 44, Folder MS folder)
    -Includes Jacob Gould and J. B. Sumner
  - Sumner in office at Savage Hall, 1951 (Box 5)
  - Dr. Sutherland Simpson (Box 5)
  - George F. Gray, 1951 (Box 5)
  - Wilder D. Bancroft (3 copies), 1948 (Box 5)
  - Dr. and Mrs. Philip B. Haw and Sumner (Box 5)
  - Bennett R. Macmillan (Box 5)
  - Uppsala, Sweden - Nobel Prize Ceremonies, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Willard Straight Hall, Cornell Library and Bell Tower, Mr. de Grassi and Dr. Abbe near library (Box 5)
  - Cornell Campus - Horse Barn, 1942 (Box 5)
  - Savage Hall (also excavation for), 1946-1947 (Box 5)
  - Catalase Crystals - Phenolphthalein (1 large, 22 small, neg.) (Box 5)
  - Urease (Box 5)
  - Tswett Column (Box 5)
  - Catalase Crystals (photos and glass slides) (Box 5)
  - Other Beef Liver Crystalline Proteins (photos and slides) (Box 5)
  - Other Beef Liver Crystalline Proteins (slides) (Box 5)
  - Jack Bean Protein (other than urease) (slides) (Box 5)
  - Glass slides in wooden boxes (Box 6)
  - Glass slides in wooden boxes (Box 7)
  - Glass slides in wooden boxes (Box 8)
  - Glass slides in wooden boxes (Box 9)
- Series V. Recognitions
  - Certificate: Phi Kappa Phi (Box 5)
  - Bound Volume: Nobel Prize (Box 5)
  - 2 diplomas, 1948-1949 (Mapcase-folder 1)